Guide to the Foster Hall Collection, 1800-1952 CAM.FHC.2011.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Stephen Foster, 1837-1900; I.
  - Manuscripts, 1837-1863; 4.
    - Stephen Foster's Correspondence, 1837-1863
      - To his sister, Henrietta, March 19, 1855; A308; 1 folders
        You will be delighted to hear that I have received a letter from Dunning written at New Orleans conveying cheering news with regard to his health. He says that he is so much improved in health as to feel that he will ultimately overcome his complaint entirely, at the same time saying that he has suffered a great deal both in body and mind. His letter is full of affection expressed towards us all and of deep feelings on the subject of our dear mother's death. He hopes to visit us all in the summer, naming in this connection Youngstown, Allegheny City & Philada. Pa's health has been excellent ever since you left us. I have taken great care to see that he is treated with regularity and system. Biddy is my main stay, and is even a much better girl than I had expected to find her. Margaret is also an excellent girl. I found, for many reasons, that Mrs. Gibson was any thing but an assistance to us, though her intentions for the most part were good. She and Carry, her daughter, have gone home. I get along much better without having any strangers in the house except as servants. I hope dear Mary's health is firmly established by this time. Mit. is in Philada. With love to all.
        Jane sends her love. She is making summer dresses for Marion. Please let me hear for you.
      - To his friend, Billy Hamilton, January 16, 1857; A311; 1 folders
        Pittsburgh Jan. 16, 1857
        Dear, Billy,
        Your letter from Point Pleasant has been received, and I am glad to know the whereabouts of the great North American ballad singer. When can you promise to appear again before a Pittsburgh audience? Masonic Hall can be had now. I have also had an engagement, tendered me, but I declined. Kleber is going to give a concert and he has offered me the post of first anvil player in the "Anvil Chorus" from a new opera. I was unwilling to go through the course of training and dieting requiste for the undertaking, and consequently declined. I understand he has sent to Europe for a "first anvil." We have had another little political brush in the election of Mayor, but there was very little excitement.
        I have not yet received the Cincinnati Gazette and suppose that puff has not appeared. I will send you by this mail a copy of "Jeanie with the light brown hair" if I can find a copy. Mit is now living with us. James Buchanan returned yesterday from a long visit home. Mrs. F. and Miss Maggie are quite well. Your account of your appearance on stage rather got them.
        I am much obliged to you for that dog, "Rat-trap" as we call him, on account of his well known ferocity toward those animals. You must pardon me if I inform you that he is now with us no more. He continued to devour shoes, stockings, spools, the Cat and everything else that he could find lying around loose. At last we held a council of war, and thought we would put him in the cellar. There he stayed for three weeks and howled all the time, and would have howled until now if I had not let him out. I was afraid the neighbors would inform on us for keeping a nusiance. Solitary confinement did not agree with him. He lost his appetite. Then I gave him some garlic as you had instructed me. This gave him a sort of diarrhea, and he got into Mit's room and relieved himself on his bed, then he scattered his dirty shirts over the floor, sprinkled his shoes and played hob generally. This performance seemed to bring him to his appetite, for that same evening he stole a whole beef steak off the Kitchen table and swallowed it raw. We concluded that this was too much to stand even from "Friendships offering," so I made up my mind to trade him off. John Little had a friend in Chicago who wanted just such a dog, so he gave me a very fine Scotch terrier eighteen months old for him. "Trap" is enjoying the lakebreezes. I am very much obliged to you for that dog.
        James Buchanan has just come in to see me, so here I will wind up.
        Your Friend
        S.C. Foster
      - To his brother, Morrison, October 22, 1858; A337; 1 folders
        Pittsburgh Oct. 22/58
        Dear Mit
        I recd. the medicine you sent me for Bill Blakely and took it over to him. I also left with him all the directions contained in both your letters. Bill looks worse than when I last saw him, and he told me that he had been sinking for the past two weeks more than formerly. He says that your medicine is much better than that by the same name which he has been using. I will call on Cupid and get the shaving fixings.
        If you are not in any particular hurry for Benton's books I would like to read a little in them before sending them to you.
        Please give my love to Brother William and ask him whether he would like to have me send him the Assembly books that Pa had. We are all well—
        Your Affec. bro
        If you have the book containing Scotch melodies I wish you could send it to me, I will return it to you. I have sent to F.P. & Co. the song "Sadly to mine heart appealing" (Lyrics suggested on hearing an old Scottish melody) and would like to select an old tune for the introductory symphony. If you have not the book probably you can tell me where to find one.
        S.C.F.
      - To his brother, Morrison, November 2, 1858; A310; 1 folders
        Pittsburgh Nov. 2, 1858
        Neither Henry nor I feel inclined to go to Cincinnati, but our old friend Tom Smith says he will go willingly. I told him he should have his passage free if he paid for his meals. This he has agreed to. I will pay the $3 – extra passage. Will this suit? If so let me know and send me the pass, and I will notify Mary when to be at Salem.
        By the way, there is an excellent man named James Gray here who desires to see him family in Cincinnati. He is a hard working Glass blower. He says he could get off from duty if he could only afford to pay his passage. If it can be done send a pass for him. I like his general character.
        The pass for Mr. Gray will have no reference to Tom Smith's business.
      - To his brother, Morrison, November 11, 1858; A338; 1 folders
        Pittsburgh, Nov. 11, 1858
        Mary Wick, Jane, Marion and I start tomorrow for Cincinnati on Billy Hamilton's boat, the "Ida May." We all went to see Miss Davenport last night at the "old" theatre. We will stirr old John McClellan up in Cincinnati, make the children sing and bring in Billy's bass voice. The trip will be a recreation and variety for me. Siss gets along very well since mother's death. We had a nice duck supper with her the other evening. She had plenty of jokes about Andy as usual.
        Our old friend Bill Blakely died this morning. There is a very favorable notice in the evening's "Chronicle." I posted O'Neil on the matter. When I saw him last he said he wondered whether he would ever see you again.
        Your Affectionate Brother
      - To his brother, Morrison, June 13, 1859; A339; 1 folders
        Pittsburgh June 13, 1859
        My dear brother Mit.
        Yesterday my neighbor who has the Daguerreotype establishment invited me to have my picture taken. I think it is rather good and I send it to you, my dear brother.
        Did you receive my letter intended for Mr. Bateman, and did you forward it?
        I sent off a first rate song that other day to Firth, Pond & Co. When I receive a printed copy I will send it to you.
        Your affectionate bro.
      - To his brother, Morrison, August 15, 1859; A340; 1 folders
        Dear Mit,
        I went to Baden on Saturday, and took Jane with me. I saw Mr Deerdorf who said that the crops had been bad and dull payments &c &c. In short, he had not the money. He had not recd "the scratch of a pen" from you in a long time that you had not demanded the money when it was due, &c. I asked him when he would be ready with the money, he said, about the 1st of October. I told him to leave it with Henry. We took dinner and tea at Mr. Aderson's. He was not at home, but the girls were. Mrs. Berry (the youngest daughter) is very pretty and entertaining, being a combination of Mary Wick, Mary McClelland, Mrs Mitchell, Mrs. Woods, &c.
        Much love to all
        S. C. Foster
      - To his brother, Morrison, May 31, 1860; A342; 1 folders
        Warren, O. May 31, 1860.
        Herewith I send you a draft on Firth Pond & Co. for $50 – which I wish you to hold for ten days, and, if you can conveniently, please send me the amount by return mail. There will be no trouble about payment of the draft. I have only one song to finish in the time mentioned. I desire you to pay Mr. Shoenberger (the landlord) at the end of the month as I engaged to do, and have told him that I would pay him when I hear from Cleveland.
        I received a very cheering letter yesterday from F.P. & Co. and feel in good spirits generally.
        Jesse Thornton arrived yesterday looking very well. We all did our best to give him a hearty welcome, and you never saw such a happy family. He informed me that Jessie (yours) was in Cleveland, therefore I infer that you have been in Pittsburgh since I saw you. I expect to start for New York, before very long and hope to see you both.
      - To his brother, Morrison, April 27, 1860; A341; 1 folders
        Warren, O. Apl. 27, 1860
        Dear Mit.
        Please send me by return mail $12 – I have received from F.P. & Co. a letter stating that they cannot advance me any more money till I send them the songs now due them (about two as I make the calculation) as our present agreement is about expiring. They show a disposition to renew agreement, but, very properly required payment in music before any new arrangement. I have entered into an arrangement with a new house for part of my music, but, as the terms are not entirely fixed, I cannot well draw on them just now. I expect to be in Cleveland very soon on my way to New York, and will be able to settle with you. I require this amount for little washing bills &c. which are, you know, the most perplexing. Please send the amt. immediately in receipt of this.
        Jane and Marion are well, also Etty's family. I am very well, but had, as I supposed a slight touch of ague yesterday. I think today that it was only a false alarm. I have written two songs since I have been in Warren and have two under way, but do not feel inclined to send them off half made up. Much love to Jessie.
        Your affec. bro
      - To his brother, Henry, December 6, 1862; A309; 1 folders
        My dear brother,
        Send the money for the pictures to care of John J. Daly 419, Grand Street.
        I received a nice letter from Willie Foster but have not yet answered him. When you write, tell me all the news you can think of. You must remember it is nearly three years since I was in Pittsburgh.
        I am very well and have been working quite industriously, but pay, these times, especially in music, is very poor.
        Your affec. bro.
      - To George W. Birdseye, February 11, 1863; A334; 1 folders
        I will arrange Mr. Cooper's melody when my hand gets well.
        Very Respy Yours
      - To J.B. Russell, January 28, 1857; A350; 1 folders
      - From Firth Pond & Company, September 12, 1849; C916
        This copy is a photocopy; the original is held by the Library of Congress, call number ML95 .F8.
      - To E.P. Christy, February 23, 1850; C917; A photostat of the letter is located at C999
        This copy is a photocopy. The original is held by the Library of Congress, call number ML95 .F8.
      - To E.P. Christy, June 20, 1851; C997; Item is a photostat.
      - From Mrs. Esten Cooke to Stephen Foster, July 26, 1859; C961
      - To E.P. Christy, June 12, 1851; c999; Item is a photostat.
      - From Mrs. Esten Cooke to Stephen Foster, July 26, 1859; C998
      - From Stephen Foster to Morrison Foster, April 27, 1849; D001; Item is a typed copy.
        Cincinnati April 27, 1849
        You must be tired waiting for an answer to the many favors which I have received from you not the least welcome of which was that, introducing to my acquaintance Signor Biscaccianti and his accomplished lady. I called on Madame B. and was as much delighted by her conversation and agreeable manners as I was subsequently by her singing at her concerts. She spoke very affectionately of you and the ladies who accompanied you on the occasion of your visit to her as if you had been her own brother as well as mine. Her concerts were very well attended here, indeed such was her encouragement, notwithstanding the formidable opposition carried on at the theatre by Mr. Macready, that she expressed an intention to return after she should have made a visit to Louisville where she is now singing.
        In writing to Gil Smith please say that I am very much grieved at having been the cause of so much trouble and humiliation to him on account of a miserable song, and tell him that if he has not already burned the copyright (and I certainly should have done) he may give it to Mess Firth & Pond any time that he may be in the neighborhood of No. 1 Franklin Square. If they will him 10$ 5$ or even 1$ for it, let him make a donation of the amt to the Orphans Asylum or any other charitable or praiseworthy institution. Mess F. & P have written to me for the song. ("Nelly Was a Lady" was the song here referred to.)
        I did not read the articles which I marked in the Atlas but supposed them to be written in the usual style of the editor whom I consider the most powerful and talented writer in the West, therefore you must not blame me if he treated of Kamtchatka or Noatka sound, I merely desired that you should have a touch of his quality.
        Tell Ma she need not trouble herself about the health of Cincinnati as our weather here is very healthy the cholera not having made its appearance. There is something about letter writing which so runs away with my hand that my ideas can find no interpreter I think I must study photography which will probably remove this blind bridle orthography, and give my brain a lighter harness to work in.
        With love to all, Your affectionate brother Stephen
  - Post-Mortem Royalty Statements & Correspondence, 1864-1900; 5.
    This subseries includes records and correspondence regarding Foster's earnings after his death. These were all records kept and maintained by Foster's brother, Morrison, who entered into an agreement with each of Foster's original publishers that secured any earnings for Foster's widow, Jane, and his daughter, Marion, and who took it upon himself to re-register many of Foster's songs so that they remained under copyright after their initial expiration. Of greatest interest perhaps are Morrison's early letters with William A. Pond, a publisher who tried to avoid paying Foster's heirs. Morrison refused to relent to their bullying tactics. Also of interest is Morrison's attempt to restore his brother's name on "Old Folks at Home" which had been attributed to E.P. Christy.
    - July 1884 statement of royalties from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1884; D196
      $4.35 in royalties.
    - Letter from William A. Pond enclosed with January 1884 royalty statement, February 4, 1884; D197
      Two payments for $49.50 each.
    - Cover letter for January 1888 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., April 13, 1888; D198
      $103.50 in royalties.
    - Cover letter for July 1888 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 26, 1888; D199a
      $178 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1888 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1888; D199b
    - Cover letter for January 1889 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., March 14, 1889; D200a
      $61.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - January 1889 Royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1889; D200b
    - July 1889 Royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1889; D201
      $99 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - January 1888 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1888; D202
      $103.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - Cover letter for January 1887 royalties from William A. Pond & Co., February 9, 1887; D203
    - Cover letter for January 1886 royalties from William A. Pond & Co., January 21, 1886; D204
      $42.15 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - Cover letter for July 1886 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., August 30, 1886; D205a
      $47.25 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1886 royalties statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1886; D205b
    - Cover letter for July 1887 royalties, September 8, 1887; D206
      Two checks for $77.25.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, June 21, 1879; D207
      Letter to Morrison saying that the copyrights don't need to be entered in the name of Foster's heirs. Morrison's response is on the back of the letter, indicating Pond is mistaken.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, August 8, 1879; D208
      Requesting that Morrison redraw agreements to fix errors. Wants to be able to sell copies on hand he has of songs that were printed before the copyright expiration. Claims Stephen owed them over $1,000 at the time of his death. Morrison's response on back includes that he made the changes and indicated that there is no way he will permit them to continue to sell songs with expired copyrights.
    - Letter from William A. Pond to Morrison Foster, September 2, 1879; D209
      Returning signed agreement, with a few more corrections. Insisting Morrison allow them to sell copies on hand without providing royalties to heirs, especially since Stephen owed them $1,000.
    - Letter from Morrison Foster to William A. Pond & Co., September 4, 1879; D210
      Indicating the check supposed to be enclosed in his Sept. 2nd letter was not there, but even if it were, it would not be accepted until the matter about royalties on songs with expired copyrights has been resolved. Until all is resolved the contract remains in abeyance. He cannot fathom why they keep bringing up the money Stephen owed them when Stephen made them thousands of dollars.
    - Letter from William A. Pond to Morrison Foster, September 9, 1879; D211
      Seeking to correct Morrison's claim that they were planning on printing a large quantity of songs just before the copyrights expired and selling them -- what Pond wants to do is merely get rid of the stock they already have. Also enclosed the missing check. Morrison's response on back indicates he agrees.
    - Letter from Jane (Foster) Wiley to Morrison Foster, August 9, 1888; D212
      Acknowledging royalty checks from Ditson that he sent to Jane for her and Marion. She will present Marion with her check when she visits hers and will have her acknowledge the receipt.
    - Letter from Jane (Foster) Wiley to Morrison Foster, July 31, 1888; D213
      Acknowledging receipt of royalty check.
    - Postcard from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, June 27, 1879; D214
      Cannot respond to Morrison's request until he answers his.
    - January 1890 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1890; D215
      $46.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1896 Royalty Statement from William A. Pond & Co., August 1, 1896; D216
      $19.80 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1895 Royalty Statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1895; D217
      $90.75 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - January 1896 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., February 1, 1896; D218
      $37.20 in royalties.
    - July 1894 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1894; D219
      $116.25 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - Cover letter for July 1893 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 5, 1893; D220
      $75.00 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1893 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1893; D221
    - Royalty statement for January, 1893, from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1893; D222
    - Cover letter for July 1892 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., October 27, 1892; D223a
      $76.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - July 1892 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1892; D223b
    - Cover letter for January 1892 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., May 23, 1892; D224a
      $67.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - January 1892 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1892; D224b
    - July 1891 royalty statement and cover letter from William A. Pond & Co., November 23, 1891; D225
    - Letter from William A. Pond to Morrison Foster, May 3, 1890; D226
      Forwarding request from J.S. Unger of Reading, PA, to use the airs of "Old Dog Tray" and "My Old Kentucky Home" in a military band arrangement.
    - Cover letter for July 1890 royalty statement, October 13, 1890; D227
      $108.25 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - Letter from Jane (Foster) Wiley to Morrison Foster, September 7, 1889; D228
    - July 1890 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., July 1, 1890; D229
      $108.75 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - January 1891 royalty statement from William A. Pond & Co., January 1, 1891; D230
      $82.50 in royalties. Note in Morrison's hand that he distributed it to Jane & Marion.
    - Letter from William A Pond to Morrison Foster, May 11, 1890; D231
      Responding to a Library of Congress letter claiming that two copies of "Oh, Boys Carry me 'long" hadn't been deposited as required. Pond forwards the letter claiming they did.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, June 18, 1879; D232
      Requesting to republish Foster's songs. Morrison's response on back indicates that he is fine, but would like a $100 advance and 3 cent per copy royalty.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, June 3, 1879; D233
      Clarifying past royalty agreements and how royalty rate was tied to price. Proposes $50 advance instead of $100. Morrison's response on back: requests 3 cent uniform royalty regardless of price. Asking for a list of songs that Ponds owns that expire that year and asks that Pond reenter them for copyright in Jane and Marion's names. Suggests it would be great for them to issue a cheap volume of Foster's melodies.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, May 28, 1879; D234
      List of songs that have already expired. List of what they will reenter in their name.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, May 19, 1879; D235
      More discussion of copyright renewals, new royalty agreement for reissues.
    - Letter from William A. Pond & Co. to Morrison Foster, July 8, 1879; D236